Inventory of the Daniel W. Knowlton family papers, 1864-1966, (bulk 1896-1966)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Daniel W. Knowlton family papers
1864-1966, (bulk 1896-1966)
Knowlton, Daniel W., 1881-1969
03419
2.55 2.55 cubic ft. (3 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The Daniel W. Knowlton family papers predominately consist of the personal and professional papers of Colorado lawyer Daniel W. Knowlton, Jr. (1881-1969). Also included are diaries from Daniel W. Knowlton, Sr. (1846-1897) and family pictures.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection has been minimally processed and divided into two series.
Series I. Family Papers, 1864-1865, 1896-1966.
Series II. Photographs and Scrapbooks, undated.
Biography of the Knowlton family
Daniel W. Knowlton, Jr. was born in 1881, and graduated from Harvard University in 1903. Knowlton practiced law in Colorado Springs, Colorado from 1910-1917, at which time he joined the U.S. Army’s 148th Field Artillery Regiment for World War I. After the war he served as a counsel for the Interstate Commerce Commission, and from 1928-1952 he was the Commission’s chief counsel. He passed away in March, 1969.
Daniel W. Knowlton, Sr. was born September 7, 1846 in West Upton, Massachusetts. He briefly attended Harvard University in 1864-1865, and married Mary Anna Frost in 1873. He passed away on August 27, 1897.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the Knowlton family papers consist of the personal and professional papers of Daniel Knowlton, Jr. These papers include his legal work in Colorado Springs, Colorado (1910-1917), his work as chief counsel of the Interstate Commerce Commission (1928-1952), correspondence, writings, and his World War I era military manuals. Other materials included in the collection are the college diaries of Daniel Knowlton, Sr., (with entries on the Civil War and the assassination of Abraham Lincoln), and family photographs and genealogical information.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Daniel W. Knowlton at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from Daniel G. Knowlton in 1970 and 2007.
Access Terms
Knowlton family.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865--Assassination.; United States. Army. Field Artillery.; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission.; Harvard University--Students--Diaries.; United States. Supreme Court.; Practice of law--Colorado.; Practice of law--United States.; World War, 1914-1918--Personal narratives, American.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Colorado Springs (Colo.)--History.; Massachusetts--Genealogy.; Diaries.; Photograph albums.; Scrapbooks.;;; Knowlton, Daniel W., 1846-1897.
Social Life and Customs; Politics, Government, and Law; Civil Procedure and Courts; Laws and Legislation; Military; Diaries
Container List
- Series I. Family Papers, 1864-1865, 1896-1966
  - Diaries - Daniel Knowlton, Sr., 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diaries - Daniel Knowlton, Sr., 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - World War I Reminiscences - Daniel Knowlton, Jr., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family correspondence., 1896-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Legal Papers - Daniel Knowlton, Jr., 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Legal Papers - Daniel Knowlton, Jr., 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Supreme Court Briefs - Daniel Knowlton, Jr. Six Volumes, 1926-1944 (Box 1)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission, circa 1928-1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission, circa 1928-1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission, circa 1928-1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission, circa 1928-1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Certificates and Organizations - Daniel Knowlton, Jr., 1900-1927 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1865, 1902-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Papers - Daniel Knowlton, Jr., 1899-1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Military Manuals, 1911-1917 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Books, 1909-1918 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Books, 1944 (Box 3)
  - World War I, Western Front Map, 1918 (Box 3)
- Series II. Photographs and Scrapbooks, undated
  - Photographs, 1915-1967, undated (Box 3)
  - Photograph Album/Scrapbook, undated (Box 3)